So with all of this CDing around,
حسنًا، مع وجود CD هذه كلها،
it's possible to get kind of lost.
من المحتمل وجود نوع من فقدان البيانات.
Depending on your system, the shell prompt
حسب نظامكم، قد تخبركم مطالبة shell
might or might not tell you what directory you're in,
بالدليل الذي أنتم به الآن وقد لا تخبركم بذلك،
but there is a command that will always tell you,
لكن يوجد أمر سيخبركم بذلك دائمًا،
the pwd command.
وهو أمر pwd.
That stands for Print Working Directory.
ويرمز ذلك إلى طباعة دليل العمل.
The working directory is another word for whatever directory
دليل العمل هو كلمة مرادفة لأي دليل
the shell is currently looking at.
يفحصه أمر shell الآن.
It's the default directory for commands like ls.
فهو الدليل الافتراضي لأوامر مثل ls.
And it's the default place that shell commands
وهو المكان الافتراضي الذي ستبحث فيه أوامر shell عن
will look for data files.
ملفات البيانات.
You'll notice that the names of directories
وستلاحظون أن أسماء الأدلة
are separated by slashes.
مفصولة بأشرطة مائلة.
The Unix system uses the forward slash, not the backslash,
ويستخدم نظام Unix الأشرطة المائلة للأمام، وليست الأشرطة المائلة للخلف،
to separate the names of directories.
للفصل بين أسماء الأدلة.
Forward slash is the same one you've seen in URLs on the web.
الشرطة المائلة هي نفس الشرطة التي رأيتموها في عناوين URL على الويب.
This whole string, composed of several directory
تسمى هذه السلسلة بأكملها، التي تضم أسماء العديد من الأدلة
names separated by slashes, is called a path.
المفصولة بشرطات مسارًا.
There are a few special directory names.
يوجد قليل من أسماء الأدلة الخاصة.
You've seen dot, dot before, it means
لقد رأيتم قبل ذلك وجود نقطتين، ويعني أنه
the parent directory, the directory
الدليل الأصلي، أي الدليل
that this directory is inside.
الذي يوجد هذا الدليل بداخله.
There's also dot, just means the current directory.
ويوجد أيضًا النقطة، ويعني الدليل الحالي.
ls dot is just the same as ls.
يكون الأمر ls dot مماثلًا للأمر ls.
And the shell also has a shortcut, the tilde, which
كما يوجد اختصار أيضًا للأمر shell وهو التلدة
stands for my home directory.
ويرمز ذلك إلى الدليل الرئيسي.
Like regardless of what directory your CD'd into,
وبغض النظر عن الدليل الذي يوجد به CD،
ls tilde will list your home directory.
سيذكر ls تلدة الدليل الرئيسي.